Welcome to the Deep Dive. Today we're exploring a theory that, well, it aims to explain just
about everything. Yeah, it's pretty ambitious stuff. From the universe's basic structure,
how your brain processes information, even where AI might be heading. Sounds a bit like
science fiction, doesn't it? It does, but it's a serious proposal. It comes from a research group,
Flixian, and they call it the Relativistic Scalar Vector Plenum, RSVP for short. RSVP theory. Okay.
And what's really fascinating, I think, is how they weave together ideas from
physics, theoretical physics, neuroscience, and AI research. It's all meant to be one coherent
framework. And where are we getting this information? You mentioned Flixian. Yeah,
exactly. We've got a whole set of their recent papers and even some pretty interesting informal
notes they've put out, all very current, July 2025. Okay. So our mission today is to really get into
this ambitious, maybe even audacious theory. We'll look at the core ideas, how it wants to
redefine things like consciousness, the cosmos, and why they think it offers a better path for AI.
You know, more biologically plausible, maybe more ethically sound. That's the claim.
All right. Prepare for some serious mind bending, I think. Decorate.
So let's start at the heart of it. RSVP theory. Yeah.
You said it's built on, what, three fundamental fields? Yeah.
Like building blocks? Exactly. Three core components. Think of them as the basis for
this new conceptual reality they're proposing. Okay. What are they?
Well, RSVP models pretty much any system, physical, cognitive, even narrative structures,
like stories through how these three fields interact. And this happens over, you know,
standard four-dimensional space time. Right.
So first you've got the scalar field. The Greek letter phi, oh way, this is like the what?
Right. Semantic density, energy concentration, maybe neural activation strength. It's the
substance, the meaning in a given spot. But what?
Second, the vector field, little v. This captures flow, information flow, attention direction,
entropy gradients even. It's the how or where to. It directs movement, influence.
The directionality. Makes sense.
And finally, there's the entropy field. This quantifies the ambiguity, the disorder,
the uncertainty. You know, how much chaos or how much order is there right here, right now?
Chaos versus order.
And a really key idea in RSVP is that the system is always, always trying to minimize this entropy.
It wants to move towards more coherent, more structured states.
Okay. So those are the three pieces. What does it mean for how they actually work together?
How do they interact?
Yeah. They're not just sitting there separately. They're dynamically coupled. That means they
constantly influence each other through things like diffusion, you know, spreading out,
advection being carried along by the flow, and feedback loops, lots of feedback loops. And the
evolution, how these fields change over time, it's governed by equations. Coupled partial differential
equations, actually. It's a bit like how physics describes fluids moving or particles interacting.
So there's real math behind it.
Oh, yeah. Definitely. And the goal is always that drive towards lower entropy. That's what allows
order, structure, meaning to emerge from what might look like just random noise at first.
Okay. Interesting. Immersions from reducing entropy. Let's try and make this more concrete.
Our brains. How does this apply to neuroscience?
Right. So the brain. Neuroscience has puzzled over cortical columns for a long time.
Those vertical clusters of neurons.
Right. Exactly. You can see them anatomically. But figuring out their consistent function has
been tricky, especially because they vary quite a bit, you know, between species, even between
individuals. Horton and Adams pointed this out back in 2005.
So they're not identical units doing the same job everywhere.
Doesn't seem like it. And that raises the question, if they aren't fixed functional units,
what are they?
Okay. And RSVP has an answer.
It offers a reinterpretation. RSVP sees columns not as rigid structures, but as, get this,
emergent coherence tiles.
Emergent coherence tiles. Okay. Unpack that.
Think of them like dynamic patterns. They just sort of arise, self-organize from the interplay
of those three fields, die, V, and S. But they're shaped by specific constraints.
Like what's coming in from our senses.
Exactly. Sensory inputs or even the brain's energy budget. The scalar field, it forms these
low entropy attractor spots where the entropy S gets minimized, where information gets really
focused and ordered. And that's what forms these tiles, these apparent columns.
Ah, so their variability makes sense then. They're context-dependent solutions, not fixed hardware.
Precisely. It depends on the conditions, not some rigid genetic blueprint.
That's a really different way of looking at brain structure.
It is. And it connects nicely with another idea called geometric Bayesianism with sparse
heuristics, or GBSH.
GBSH.
Which basically argues that the brain's amazing efficiency, its sparsity, comes from metabolic
constraints. It has to save energy.
Because the brain uses so much power.
A huge amount. And studies, like by pervs and colleagues more recently, show these conserved
ratios column width to cortical thickness across different species. GBSH and RSVP suggest these
ratios aren't genetic dictates, but geometric scaling laws, driven by minimizing energy.
Wow. Okay. And you mentioned something else, amplitwist operators. That sounds very sci-fi.
Yeah, it does sound a bit out there, doesn't it? But it's a really neat mathematical idea
they use.
What do they do?
Well, what's cool is they combine two things. Amplitude scaling.
Like turning the volume up or down?
Kind of, yeah. Like gain control in your senses.
Yeah.
Adjusting sensitivity. And they combine that with phase rotation.
Phase rotation.
And like waves. Or tuning.
Exactly. Like a neuron changing its tuning or its oscillation pattern.
So these operators, they apply a local transformation. They sort of twist and scale
the neural representations. Imagine zooming in or out on a mental map or rotating your
perspective on something. And the idea is that by composing these operations recursively,
layer after layer in the cortex, the brain can perform really complex functions.
Spatial reasoning. Grouping objects together visually.
So the brain's flexibility isn't from fixed modules, but from dynamically tweaking these
geometric transformations.
That's the argument. It's a much more fluid picture of how the brain computes and adapts.
Fascinating. Okay, let's pivot from biology to artificial intelligence.
Yeah.
AI.
Right.
The current big thing is transformer architectures, right? Powering models like ChatGPT, Bernie.
They rely heavily on this mechanism called self-attention.
They do.
But RSVP theory or affliction seems quite critical of that approach.
What's their issue with self-attention?
Yeah. They have a paper called Attention Considered Harmful. Strong title.
Oh, okay.
Their argument is basically that while transformers work well on current hardware, like GPUs, that
dense self-attention mechanism, it's fundamentally not how biology does it. They argue it's more
like a graph neural network over a fully connected graph, or maybe a shallow recurrent network with a fixed
look ahead. And this, they say, violates something crucial. The natural sparsity principle, NSP.
Natural sparsity principle. You mentioned sparsity with the brain's energy use. Tell us more
about this principle. So, the NSP basically states that biological cognition has to be sparse.
There are critical constraints forcing it.
Like the energy cost.
Exactly. That's number one. Metabolic cost. Your brain burns something like 10 to the 14 ATP molecules
per second. It's incredibly expensive. It absolutely cannot afford dense all-to-all computations
like transformers often do. Sparse activation is key to saving energy.
So, dense attention is just too wasteful biologically?
Way too wasteful, and creates redundant calculations. Second constraint, environmental
noise. Biology operates in a noisy world. Sparse pathways actually improve the signal-to-noise
ratio, makes the system more robust.
Okay. And third?
Thermodynamic gradients. That drive to minimize entropy we talked about, that naturally favors
sparse ordered representations over dense, potentially chaotic ones.
So, transformers are powerful, maybe computationally, but they're not thinking like us because they
violate these fundamental biological or even physical constraints.
That's the core critique, yeah.
Yeah.
They're not respecting the sparsity that seems inherent to natural intelligence.
So, what's the RSVP alternative for AI then? If not attention, then what?
They propose a few interconnected ideas. One is relevance activation theory, or RAT.
RAT.
Okay. Here, attention isn't a built-in mechanism. It's an emergent property that arises from
those RSVP fields interacting recursively.
How does that work?
The scalar field, F-wa, encodes the meaning, the semantics. The entropy field, S, helps suppress
noise and guide the system towards sparse solutions. And the vector field, V, directs the flow of
activation, the spotlight, if you will. It emerges from the dynamics.
Interesting. And you mentioned another one.
Yeah. Aspect relegation theory, or RT. This tries to explain how we shift between different
modes of thinking. You know, slow, deliberate, System 2 thinking versus fast, automatic, System
1 processing.
Kahneman's concepts.
Right. Exactly. In RSVP terms, RT describes this shift as the system learning to reduce entropy
gradients and stabilize the vector field pathways for tasks we practice a lot. Things become automatic
because the flow gets streamlined and efficient.
So it's about learning efficient pathways within these fields.
Exactly.
Yeah. Completely different from just adding more layers or parameters.
It's a fundamentally different architectural approach grounded in these field dynamics
and efficiency principles.
And does this different approach tie into the challenge of controlling AI, this idea of a
controlled AI takeoff?
Absolutely. That's a huge part of the motivation, I think. The question is critical. How do we guide
AI that's becoming potentially super intelligent?
Right. How do we keep it aligned?
RSVP contributes to what they frame as a three-tiered framework for a controlled AI takeoff. It's
quite sophisticated.
Three tiers. Okay. What are they?
Tier one is criticality. This is about when an AI system should act or maybe even learn.
The idea is to tune AI systems to operate near the edge of chaos.
The edge of chaos. Like not too rigid, not too random.
Precisely. It's thought to be a state where information processing is optimal. And here's
the really interesting part. They suggest that collective human preferences, maybe even
nonverbal signals like societal mood or protests, could actually modulate these criticality thresholds.
So society could collectively tap the brakes or hit the gas on AI development.
That's the idea. Dynamically adjusting the AI's operating point based on collective sentiment.
Wow. Okay. Tier one is when? What's tier two?
Tier two is predictive coding. This manages how the AI acts. It's inspired by how our brains
work, constantly trying to predict sensory input and minimize prediction errors.
Like the Bayesian brain idea.
Very much so. AI systems would continuously model and predict human preferences.
Crucially, they penalize themselves for being overconfident in their predictions about us.
So they have to be cautious about assuming what we want.
Exactly. And explicit human feedback votes, dialogues, collective decisions could directly
adjust these internal predictions. If the AI's predictions about our preferences are way off,
maybe training gets paused automatically.
Built-in alignment checks.
Okay. And tier three.
Tier three brings an RSVP directly. This is about ensuring what is meaningful. It models the AI's
decisions and outputs, not just as data, but as ripples in this underlying semantic plenum,
this field of meaning.
Okay.
So you'd use RSVP metrics, things like field coherence or nogentropy, which is like the opposite
of entropy, a measure of order to make sure that the AI's growth and actions actually preserve
meaning. That it doesn't just generate technically correct nonsense or pursue goals that are semantically
hollow or harmful from a human perspective.
So it's about embedding purpose and meaning directly into the AI's operational principles
using this field theory.
That's the goal. Ensuring alignment with human purpose, not just optimizing some narrow technical
objective.
That is a deeply integrated approach to AI safety and governance using field theory itself.
It's definitely thinking outside the usual boxes.
Okay. Let's zoom out again. Way out. From brains and AI to the whole cosmos.
The biggest picture.
We usually think of time as this fundamental thing, right? An external river flowing forward.
Mm-hmm. The standard view.
But there are physicists like Julian Barber who've questioned that. He proposed the universe's
history isn't really an evolution in time, but maybe like a path through a static landscape
of all possible nows.
Yeah.
Configuration space.
Barber's timeless physics. Yeah. As a radical idea.
And RSVP seems to take that idea and run with it. Give it an engine.
Exactly. RSVP, especially when they combine it with another concept they call Tartan.
Tartan. What's that?
Trajectory aware recursive tiling with annotated noise. Quite a mouthful.
Okay.
But basically, Tartan helps RSVP operationalize Barber's idea. In RSVP, remember, the universe's
state at any moment is just the configuration of those VNS fields.
Right.
So time isn't some external clock ticking away. It's generated from within the system.
It emerges from the interactions of the fields and this process of entropic structuring,
of things becoming more ordered.
So the flow of time we feel, that's just an emergent property.
Yeah.
A consequence of these fields changing.
That's precisely the idea. And Tartan helps visualize this by recursively partitioning
the universe into these coherence tiles we talked about the brain. Each tile has its own local
field state, its own scale, its own entropy level.
Like little pockets of reality?
Sort of. Each one acts like a mini time capsule. Its internal structure implies a past state
and suggests a future trajectory. So time becomes localized and scale dependent. Each tile
essentially has its own internal clock ticking at its own rate based on its history and its current
entropic activity.
Wow. So no universal now.
Not in the absolute sense. This whole framework, they call it the Aletheos canonical form or ACF,
and that constant drive for change, the pressure that makes things happen,
comes from something they call universal origins theory, UET.
Okay. ACF powered by UET, generating localized time from field dynamics. That is radically different
from standard cosmology.
It really is.
Does it offer a different story for how, say, galaxies formed, how we got the large-scale
structure we see in the universe?
It does. It leads to an alternative cosmological model they call expirotic cosmology.
Expirotic.
Yeah.
Non-inflationary.
Exactly. It's a non-inflationary, non-singular model.
It doesn't rely on that super rapid expansion phase, inflation, right after the Big Bang.
And it doesn't need a contracting bounce phase like some other alternative models.
So how does structure emerge in expirosis?
The idea is that cosmic structure arises over incredibly long timescales.
Through the gradual reintegration of information that was sort of decohered or spread out very
early on. And this information, they argue, is encoded in the cosmic microwave background,
the CMB.
The CMB, the afterglow of the Big Bang. How can that be forming structures now? That
seems counterintuitive.
It does, right. But expirosis reinterprets the CMB. It's not just a passive relic. It's a
semantic horizon, an informational boundary holding the patterns from the early universe.
So the information wasn't lost?
Not truly lost, just decohered, latent within the RSVP fields. And then over these absolutely
vast timescales, Poincaré recurrence timescales.
How vast are we talking?
Astronomically vast, like 10 to the power of 50 years. Numbers that make the current age of the
universe seem like an instant.
Okay. Truly mind-boggling timescales.
On those scales, the RSVP fields dynamically recouple this lost information.
They smooth out the entropy gradients, restore coherence. And this process, the slow restructuring
based on the CMB blueprint, is what generates the large-scale homogeneity, the flatness,
the observed fluctuations in the universe.
All without needing a Big Bang singularity or inflation.
That's the claim. It bypasses the need for that initial singularity and the specific physics
of inflation. The CMB isn't just an afterglow. It's the seed crystal. And the RSVP dynamics
slowly grow the universe from it over eons.
That's a profound alternative. Does it make any predictions we could actually test? I mean,
those timescales are impossible to observe directly.
Right. That's the crucial question for any theory like this. And yes,
exploratory cosmology does make some specific, potentially testable predictions that differ
from standard inflation.
Such as...
It predicts suppressed tensor modes. Basically, very few primordial gravitational waves.
The ratio should be less than 0.01, much lower than many inflationary models predict.
Okay. That's something current and future experiments are looking for. What else?
It suggests there might be residual coherence in the CMB itself, subtle correlations or patterns
that shouldn't be there in the standard picture. This could potentially explain some of those large-scale
anomalies people have occasionally reported in the CMB data, like the axis of evil.
Hmm. Interesting. Anomalies looking for an explanation.
And finally, it predicts specific entropy flow signatures in the cosmos.
These might show up as subtle anisotropies in dark energy,
or maybe unusual correlations in the distribution of galaxies on very large scales.
So there are potential observational handles,
even if the core process takes unimaginable time?
Exactly. It's not purely philosophical speculation. There are empirical consequences.
Okay. So bringing this all together, we've gone from brain columns to AI safety to the origin of
cosmic structure and the nature of time itself. RSVP theory is trying to connect all of this.
What's the big unifying theme here?
I think the core unifying theme is this idea that information processing, whether it's in physics,
cognition, or AI, fundamentally involves these geometric structure-preserving transformations
that minimize entropy.
Like those AmpliWIST operators being a universal tool.
Exactly. They see that as potentially a fundamental mechanism for perception, representation,
inference, operating across all these different domains. It's all about fields interacting,
transforming information, and seeking coherence.
And where does something like consciousness fit into this grand picture?
Well, within this framework, consciousness isn't some spooky extra ingredient. It might emerge
naturally as a specific kind of process within these fields, perhaps a recursive entropy-modulated
traversal of the semantic field, a lawful way the system navigates and integrates information
across different interpretive landscapes.
The universe has a giant computational process constantly structuring itself and generating meaning,
maybe even consciousness.
That seems to be the direction it points, yes. A very information-centric, process-oriented view
of reality.
And Flixion, in their notes, they seem to push this even further into some really
out there, almost artistic or metaphorical territory.
I saw things like ancient lunar carvings as a cosmic API for divine computation.
What is that about?
Huh. Yeah. That's where they really explore the boundaries, maybe playfully, maybe
speculatively. It's about taking the core principles, geometric structure, information
processing, entropy minimization, and asking, where else could these apply, even in the most
extreme or abstract ways?
So lunar carvings as an API.
Right.
Is that suggesting ancient structures could literally be interfaces for some universal computation?
It's a provocative thought experiment, right? Could highly ordered, ancient patterns
literally function as interfaces. It embodies that form follows function idea at a cosmic,
almost mystical scale. It's pushing the metaphor of computation to its limits.
And what about comparing someone like Immanuel Swedenborg, the mystic, to a human LLM whose
visions were GPU overloaded hallucinations?
Again, it's applying the modern computational metaphor back onto historical phenomena.
Framing mystical experience or complex internal states as emergent results of an incredibly
complex biological computer processing vast amounts of internal data, perhaps reaching
overload or generating novel patterns. It's a way to bridge modern AI concepts with older
understandings of the mind.
So these more poetic phrases, machines that dream in reverse, paper cities that learn to
feel, they're not literal claims, but ways to express the theory's potential reach. That
meaning and structure can emerge anywhere the right field dynamics exist.
I think that's exactly it. They're metaphors suggesting that the core phenomena we associate with
life in mind, memory, learning, maybe even feeling might not be exclusively biological. They could
be inherent properties of any sufficiently complex system that organizes itself by minimizing entropy
within these fields.
So building Skynet with a theology degree or needing a firewall for your soul, it's about the deep
intertwining of computation, meaning, and maybe even ethics or purpose.
Precisely. It suggests the fundamental principles might be universal. That the logic of computation,
the drive for meaning, and the need for ethical grounding could all be deeply connected, manifesting in
ways that seem both familiar, like AI, and profoundly strange, like, well, like cosmic APIs or soulful
firewalls. It pushes us to think about computation and meaning in the broadest possible terms.
Wow. Okay. This has been quite the journey. We've really unpacked a theory, RSVP, that asks us to
rethink, well, almost everything.
It definitely casts a wide net.
From the nature of time, how our brains build reality, to the future of AI and its governance,
the relativistic scalar vector plenum is, yeah, a truly bold attempt to find a unified language,
a mathematical language for emergence across all scales.
It really challenges us, doesn't it, to look beyond fixed structures, static objects, and see the
universe, see ourselves as these dynamic, self-organizing fields, always interacting,
always striving for coherence and meaning.
A physics-grounded paradigm for intelligence itself, perhaps.
That seems to be the ultimate aim. Integrating geometry, thermodynamics, recursion, information,
all into one picture.
And it leaves us with this final thought, maybe. If understanding itself emerges from this kind of
internal recursion, resolving tensions within the system, like our brain, making sense of conflicting
inputs, then maybe something like Gödel's incompleteness theorem.
Maybe it's not an ultimate barrier.
Perhaps not a hard stop, yeah. Maybe it's more like a feature of the landscape.
Right. Just a navigable topological feature in the vast field of knowledge, as maybe affliction
might put it. Something that you work with, not something that stops you.
What single thing, after all this, really stands out to you? What connection or idea seems most provocative?
Do.
Yeah.
I do.
Do.
If.